Guide to the New-York Historical Society Collection of Scrapbooks and Clippings, 1709-1974 MS 3158
New-York Historical Society
- Austin Baxter Keep scrapbook, 1899-1901 (Offsite-box 7)
  1 volume of newspaper clippings on British royalty, the assassination of U.S. President William McKinley, and some politics.
- Frank W. Crane scrapbooks, 1899-1907 (Offsite-box 4)
  3 volumes of newspaper clippings related to New York City and its history. Source: Gift, Frank Crane, November 5, 1947.
- William G. Bates scrapbooks of menus, 1899-1915 (Offsite-box 62)
  Two volumes of menus from dinner events held by various organizations, including meetings of National Guard and veterans organizations (Bates was a colonel in the New York National Guard's 71st Regiment), such as the Society of the Cincinnati, Society of Colonial Wars, regimental reunions, etc. Gift of William Graves Bates, December 23, 1935.
- William H. Ewen scrapbook, 1899-1939 (Offsite-box 28)
  2 volumes of newspaper clippings and pictorial works on New York City. Many of the clippings relate to the history of the city, primarily from two series published in the papers: "Old New York in Pictures" and "Intimate Sketches of New York." In addition to looking at past views of New York, many clippings present contemporary (circa 1910s) views of city buildings. Source: Gift of William H. Ewen, December 1, 1958.
- Archibald Riley album of postcard correspondence, circa 1900 (Offsite-box 63)
  One album with 80 postcards sent to Archibald Riley of Hyde Park, NY. Postcards are of various types: travel, holiday greetings, humorous, illustrations, etc., with social or other notes.
- New York Stock Exchange scrapbook, 1901-1919 (Offsite-box 1)
  1 volume of newspaper clippings and some papers, including correspondence, regarding memberships and the price over time of seats on the New York Stock Exchange.
- Walter L. Bogert scrapbook, 1902-1930 (Offsite-box 2)
  1 volume of correspondence, clippings, and programs from clubs and recitals attended by Bogert. Source: Gift of Walter L. Bogert, December 31, 1953.
- "Sketches of early history of Gorham, Maine" by G.A. Miller, 1903 (Offsite-box 54)
  1 slender volume of clippings written by G.A. Miller relating a Revolutionary War era narrative concerning Gorham.
- Magazine artwork scrapbook, 1904-1905 (Offsite-box 65)
  One volume of magazine cover artwork (e.g., Collier's) and color advertisements from the magazines. Gift of Emil F. Handel, February 10, 1941.
- Charles B. Curtis scrapbook, 1905-1906 (Offsite-box 22)
  1 volume scrapbook of memorabilia concerning Curtis's travels across the United States, Europe, and Asia. Documents include tickets, pamphlets, postcards, newspaper photographs and clippings, pocket guides, maps, printed souvenirs, business cards, invitations, hotel and ship emblems, handbooks, correspondence, and ephemera.
- Frank M. Ingalls scrapbook, circa 1905-1908 (Offsite-box 24)
  1 volume of newspaper clippings. These primarily include clips from the Evening Telegram of two series of articles run in the paper in 1908: "Seeing New York with an Evening Telegram Guide" and "Seeing New York of the Olden Time." In addition there are a few miscellaneous clips from 1905-08. Source: Gift of Frank Ingalls, March 17, 1945.
- Mrs. William F. (Carolyn Sutphin?) Wyckoff scrapbook, 1905-1911 (Offsite-box 30)
  1 volume of miscellaneous newspaper clippings, many related to Jamaica, Queens, obituaries of notable figures, and historical items. There are some articles concerning William F. Wyckoff, who was 1st Vice-President of the Homestead Bank, including his "reminiscences of a worker" published in the Record in 1908. Source: Gift of Mrs. William F. Wyckoff, October 7, 1946.
- William K. Draper scrapbook (Box 1 of 2), 1905-1907 (Offsite-box 54)
  2 volumes compiled by Dr. William Kinnicut Draper (1863-1926) containing clippings from theatre, opera, symphonies, and other cultural programs; dinner menus; and other event programs. Draper was the older brother of the actress Ruth Draper, who is referenced in some of the clips. Source: Gift of the sculptor Malvina Hoffman, March 18, 1954. Hoffman's sister, Helen, was married to William Draper.
- William K. Draper scrapbook (Box 2 of 2), 1916-1920 (Offsite-box 31)
- "Of Interest to the Kanes" scrapbook, 1906-1926 (Offsite-box 67)
  One volume by an unknown compiler. The volume centers on the adult children of Marguerite Adelaide (Wolfe) Kane and her husband, Grenville Kane, their children's spouses, and members of affiliated families (e.g. Walker, McVickar, Baker), all generally associated wth Tuxedo Park, New York. (See the Marguerite Adelaide Wolfe / Mrs. Grenville Kane scrapbook above at 1878.) The album includes photographs, ephemera and clippings. One significant subject relates to home front support during World War I and to the Red Cross activities in France during WWI (including photos), where George Baker was an administrator.
- Alan R. Hawley scrapbooks on "aeronautics" (Box 1 of 3), 1906-1937 (Offsite-box 59)
  8 volumes of documents related to aviation in the early 20th century, and particularly to the Aero Club of America, balloonists, balloon races, early airplane flight, establishing the first aerial postal route between New York and Washington, DC, benefit events for World War I aviation, and the like. The volumes hold mostly newspaper clippings, but there are also many letters; telegrams; pictorial works/images; original photographs of balloons, balloonists, and other Hawley/aviation-related subjects; balloon ascension records; ephemera; and other documents. An acknowledgement letter to Hawley from N-YHS in one of the volumes indicates that a photograph of Hawley with the Wright Brothers came with the donation, but it is not known if that remains with the scrapbooks or was separated. The volumes do not run in strictly chronological order. Alan Ramsay Hawley (1869-1938) was president of the Aero Club from 1913-1919 and participated in the balloon races documented here. Source: One of the volumes was a gift of Alan R. Hawley, November 5, 1934. The other volumes were a bequest from Hawley, June 27, 1938.
- Alan R. Hawley scrapbooks on "aeronautics" (Box 2 of 3), 1906-1937 (Offsite-box 60)
- Alan R. Hawley scrapbooks on "aeronautics" (Box 3 of 3), 1906-1937 (Offsite-box 61)
- Frederick T. Steinway concert and theatre program scrapbooks (Box 1 of 2), 1908-1917 (Offsite-box 33)
  7 volumes of clippings from programs and other documents for symphonies, recitals, opera, vaudeville, and other musical performances, compiled by Frederick T. Steinway (1860-1927). Some of the volumes are embossed with Steinway's initials: "F.T.S." The clippings center on the page or portion of the document that shows the venue, works performed, and musicians. Among a wide mix of theatres/venues, the most common seem to be Carnegie Hall (e.g. Philharmonic Society of New York, Boston Symphony Orchestra), Metropolitan Opera House, and Aeolian Hall. These scrapbooks were part of the same gift to N-YHS as the Theodore E. Steinway Collection of Steinway & Sons Ephemera, circa, 1860-1986 (MS 3181).
- Frederick T. Steinway concert and theatre program scrapbooks (Box 2 of 2), 1908-1917 (Offsite-box 34)
- Charles N. Chadwick scrapbooks, 1908-1909, 1913-1919 (Offsite-box 66)
  Two volumes compiled by Charles Chadwick, who was New York City's Board of Water Supply Commissioner during this period. The first volume, dating from 1908-1909, primarily concerns drinking water resources for the city, especially plans to build the Ashokan Reservoir in the Catskills. The second volume also concerns water supply matters (1913-18), as well as clippings related to efforts to create a University of Long Island, 1913-14 (Chadwick was Chair of the Citizens Committee) and to Froebel Academy, 1913-19, with ephemera (Chadwick was President of the Board of Trustees).
- "Reminiscences of a Civil War Veteran", circa 1911-1923 (Offsite-box 24)
  1 volume compiled by Civil War veteran Morris Bornstein, a former Zouave. The album focuses principally on Bornstein in his later years when he was a custodian for the New York Secretary of State and other state positions. The scrapbook holds photographs, programs, clippings, and other documents of the veterans as well as Bornstein in his state office, during veteran parades, etc.
- Laura Valentine Sawyer scrapbook, 1912-1916 (Offsite-box 29)
  1 volume compiled by Laura Valentine Sawyer (November 23, 1895-July 3, 1977). A description of the scrapbook prepared perhaps in the 1990s by N-YHS notes that it "documents the adolescent years of an upper middle class Brooklyn girl, contains dried flowers, programs from plays and concerts, ticket stubs, photographs, a program from Saint Methodist Episcopal Church, newspaper clippings of sorority chapter parties and dances, an address book of banks and trust companies, a program from the Brighton Beach Music Hall, menu from the Catskill Mountain Hotel, clippings of college football sports news, wrappers from candy, cigarette stubs, a 1914 souvenir coupon from a trip to the top of the Woolworth Building, a 1914 Western Union Telegram, a 1915 Packer Collegiate Institute Class Day program, cube of sugar, miniature copy of the New Testament, diploma card and ribbon, baseball player favor from a graduation party, Packer Collegiate annual commencement list, graduation invitations, finger and hand prints taken by the New York City Police Department, picture of the 1916 winners of the National League [baseball] pennant, and some pen and ink sketches of ancient architectural styles on tracing paper."
- "The Autobiography of a School: The Lawrence-Smith School for Boys", 1914-1947 (Offsite-box 31)
  1 scrapbook tracing the school's history from its beginning to dissolution with some later documents. Compiled by Headmaster Clement Lawrence Smith. Subtitle of the volume is "A typical boys private school in New York City, 1914-1939." Contains a manuscript foreword by Smith; photographs of buildings and interiors, students, sports, etc.; correspondence; financial data; trustee minutes; registration list; Student Council notes; pamphlets; etc. The school was located at 168 East 70th Street from 1925 until its close in 1939. Source: Gift of Clement L. Smith, March 15, 1954.
- Edmond Charles Bonaventure scrapbooks, 1914-1935 (Offsite-box 13)
  2 volumes of clippings, invitations to events and societies, certificates, photographs, and correspondence. One of the volumes is more heavily oriented toward Bonaventure's involvement with the French Institute in the United States. The other volume is more oriented toward Bonaventure's membership in the 7th Regiment of the New York National Guard (known as the 107th Regiment during World War I) and its veterans association. Source: Gift of Edmond C. Bonaventure, May 28, 1951.
- Gordon family scrapbooks, 1915-1918 (Offsite-box 3)
  2 volumes of clippings, photographs, invitations, event placecards, and other ephemera belonging to Daniel Gordon (vol. 1) and Nathan Gordon (vol. 2).
- Russell C. Langdon clippings collection, 1917-1921 (Offsite-box 53)
  One box of newspaper pictorial pages concerning World War I, the Treaty of Versailles, Bolshevik Revolution, and other major events of the time. These papers are primarily the pictorial sections of the New York Times, The Sun, and Tribune Graphic, among others. One outlier item here is a map of U.S. locations of National Guard mobilization training camps, National Army cantonment camps, ROTC training camps, and aviation sites. Source: Gift of Brigadier General (ret.) Russell C. Langdon, July 7, 1952.
- Helen Sargent Hitchcock (Mrs. Ripley Hitchcock) scrapbook, 1917-circa 1933 (Offsite-box 17)
  1 volume scrapbook compiled by Helen Sargent Hitchcock. Most of the album relates to the Art War Relief, an auxiliary of the Red Cross during World War I, of which Hitchcock was Chairman. These documents include meeting announcements, publicity for benefit events, clippings, the first (and likely only) published report of the organization's activities, issued in 1918; and a "record of designation targets" maintained by Edith Magonigle (Mrs. H. Van Buren Magonigle), the chairman of the Painters Committee. The latter part of the album includes clippings and some ephemera related to the "Art Center," of which Hitchcock was the first president, located at 65-67 East 56th Street. Source: Gift, September 16, 1957.
- Anson F. Robinson scrapbook, 1917-1965 (Offsite-box 5)
  1 volume scrapbook regarding Anson F. Robinson's World War I service in the United States Army, 305th infantry. Contains photographs, correspondence, certificates, and clippings from the time he served, as well as programs and other material from later commemorative events.
- Comte Henrich F. de Frise scrapbook collection of calling cards, circa 1920s, undated (Offsite-box 67)
  Gift of Countess Edna Elise de Frise, March 26, 1962
- Maybell A. Winter scrapbooks (Box 1 of 3), circa 1920s-1940s (Offsite-box 19)
  5 volumes of clippings, handwritten notes, photographs, postcards, and other ephemera. Subject matter ranges from "current events" to literary material (e.g., poems) to baseball scores, etc. Source: Gift of Mrs. Garrett H. Winter (Maybell A. Winter), October 8, 1943.
- Maybell A. Winter scrapbooks (Box 2 of 3), circa 1920s-1940s (Offsite-box 20)
- Maybell A. Winter scrapbooks (Box 3 of 3), circa 1920s-1940s (Offsite-box 21)
- Margaret F. Schuman scrapbook, 1920-1922 (Offsite-box 24)
  1 volume of newspaper clippings. The clips, likely from Virginia newspapers, which is the state Schuman inscribed in the album with the date of 1922, are of miscellaneous topics but one perceptible thread relates to women, including marriage, weddings, fashion, etc. The album was originally part of N-YHS's Folk Arts Collection of November 17, 1937.
- Louis Kirschenbaum scrapbooks, 1921-1926 (Offsite-box 23)
  3 volumes of newspaper clippings on the topics of Japan and World War I (vol. 1) and Ancient Egypt (vols. 2-3). Source: Gift of Louis Kirschenbaum, March 20, 1946.
- C.G. Hine scrapbook, 1922-1924 (Offsite-box 29)
  1 volume of newspaper clippings on New York City buildings, churches, neighborhoods, topical issues, etc. Source: Gift of C.G. Hine, September 15, 1930.
- Faye Laird scrapbook, 1929-1931 (Offsite-box 41)
  Faye Laird, originally from Oklahoma, attended Columbia University in 1929-1931 to earn her Masters degree in English. She then returned home to Tulsa where she worked as a high school teacher. This 1 volume scrapbook holds materials dating from Laird's time at Columbia and in New York. There seems relatively little here about Columbia, but there are many postcards, programs from theatre and opera, ticket stubs, and other New York-related ephemera. Laird apparently traveled to Washington, DC, and to Maine/New England while on the East Coast as there are postcards and other ephemera from those places here as well. Source: Gift of Julie McShane, Laird's niece, February 1986. The biographical/context comments noted here are from a letter to N-YHS from McShane found at the front of the album.
- Clippings on Washington scrapbook, 1929-1932 (Offsite-box 6)
  1 volume that holds newspaper clippings on George Washington-related memorials, commemorations, bicentennial of his birth (1932), etc.
- Theater program clippings, 1931-1933, 1936-1939 (Offsite-box 58)
  1 volume of cutouts from programs from New York City theaters, principally the title page with theater information, play title, and cast. While most are from generally recognizable Broadway theaters, there are a few others, including the Labor Stage (1938), Federal Theatre (WPA work program, 1938), and Croton River Playhouse (1933). The album is indexed.
- George Chase Lewis scrapbook, 1931-1943 (Offsite-box 26)
  1 volume. George Chase Lewis (1876-1943) was a Colonel in the US Army. This scrapbook holds several speeches he made to civilian groups and radio addresses on topics concerning patriotism and national defense in the years just before the start of World War II and in the war's early years. There is also a 1931 speech in which he supports naming the Port Authority's new Hudson River bridge after George Washington. The scrapbook also holds a photograph of the colonel and some clippings.
- Butlers' Ball scrapbooks, 1934-1937 (Offsite-box 27)
  3 volumes of newspaper clippings regarding the first, third, and fourth of the Butlers' Balls held in New York City in 1934, 1936, and 1937. These were charity balls held for the benefit of Bellevue Hospital's family welfare social services program. Attendees included chauffeurs, gardeners, butlers, and other household workers. Source: Gift of Gustavus Swift Payne, November 17, 1955.
- Garrett H. Winter scrapbooks, 1934-1938, 1943-1949 (Offsite-box 19)
  2 volumes of clippings, all articles written by Albert W. Fribourg, member of the New York State Bar, on tax, rent, insurance, housing, and various other legal matters. Source: Gift of Garret H. Winter, Jr., January 27, 1954. Winter was Clerk of the Works for N-YHS, overseeing the late 1930s building expansion, and then N-YHS's Superintendent of Buildings until about 1960.
- Dowlin family scrapbook, 1935 (Offsite-box 3)
  1 volume scrapbook of a 1935 road trip taken by the Dowlin family around the United States, Mexico, and Canada. Depicts Winifred, Calista, and Jennie Dowlin. Contains photographs, maps, postcards, and ephemera as well as journal entries.
- Henrietta Royer Smith scrapbooks, 1936-1952 (Offsite-box 18)
  2 volumes of newspaper clippings. The bulk of these date from the 1940s and concern sports (including the deaths of Lou Gehrig and Babe Ruth), historic preservation (including Williamsburg, Virginia), V-E Day, and general notable items and obituaries. Source: Gift of Henrietta Royer Smith, October 7, 1952.
- World's Fair clippings, 1939, 1964-1966 (Offsite-box 52)
  Loose clippings and tearsheets concerning the 1939 and 1964-65 World's Fairs in New York.
- Charles W. Bryan scrapbook, 1940-1941 (Offsite-box 6)
  1 volume of clippings and pamphlets regarding the 1940 presidential campaign and its candidates, Franklin D. Roosevelt and Wendell Willkie. Source: Gift of Charles W. Bryan, October 29, 1941.
- "Bank of New York", 1950-1957 (Offsite-box 63)
  1 volume of publicity material from the Bank of New York. This is primarily booklets about their New York City office building and a series of 13 "short stories on money and banking," with a few other pieces. There is some indication that these materials were compiled and bound by N-YHS from the Bella Landauer collection.
- Dea Carroll scrapbook, 1953-1961 (Offsite-box 7)
  1 volume containing newspaper clippings and correspondence regarding singer/entertainer Dea Carroll and her related career as a fashion show host for charitable organizations and other purposes (e.g., for the New York Press Photographer's Ball and the Ruth Kirzon Group for Handicapped Children).
- Horticultural articles on scenic beauty scrapbook, circa 1955 (Offsite-box 3)
  1 volume newspaper and magazine clippings on plants, parks, and nature. Includes articles about residents of Brooklyn and the landscape of Prospect Park.
- Freedom from Hunger clippings, 1965-1972 (Offsite-box 51)
  Holds clippings individually mounted and encapsulated. Most are backed on stationery of Freedom From Hunger, a food and agriculture organization set up in 1945 to help fight hunger. These clippings relate to global food initiatives. Other clippings are mounted to other forms of paper and relate to other matters, mostly space exploration and sea treaties, with a few on the Black Panthers.
- "Deep-Sea, Dry-Cargo & Passenger Lines Calling at Ports of U.S.A.", 1970s? (Offsite-box 54)
  One slender volume of cut-outs of graphics of flags of various ship lines.
- New York City buildings clippings, 1973-1974 (Offsite-box 34)
  One packet of clippings on building-related matters, such as rent, construction, developers, etc.